Bassam (SAM) MEJLAOUI

(+212) 634-683893 | Bassam.mejlaoui@uit.ac.ma | Linkedin | Github | Leetcode | Medium | Website

SUMMARY

20+ years of academic and professional study in Data Science, Fintech, and Computational Linguistics, with 4+ years of experience in Machine Learning and AI development. Skilled in Neuroinformatics, Quantum NLP, and Fintech, with a strong command of statistical analysis, and SQL.

EXPERIENCE

Investment Analyst, Investment Banker, Financial Analyst - FinData Analytics

2024 - Present

- Expanded ROI by identifying high-yield assets from 395 options, reduced portfolio risk by 20%.
- Improved portfolio performance accuracy by 15% for 200+ high-value clients.
- Boosted client satisfaction for 150+ institutional clients, Boosted profitability by 25%.

Prompt Engineer, Machine Learning Specialist, Artificial Intelligence Developer - Sam AI Insights

2023 - Present

- Developed and optimized machine learning models, increasing prediction accuracy by 30% for 500+ data points across various datasets.
- Designed and implemented AI solutions for business automation, reducing operational costs by 20% within the first quarter of deployment.
- Collaborated with cross-functional teams to integrate advanced machine learning algorithms, enhancing product performance and user engagement by 15%.

Data Scientist, Data Collection Operator, Data Analyst - Sam Agency

2021 - 2024

- Enhanced decision-making speed across datasets of 500,000+ points, Ensured 30% improvement in data accuracy.
- Generated insights that influenced over 75 strategic client projects, Applied ML algorithms to enhance predictive analytics accuracy by 40%.
- Devised stakeholder engagement for the top 10 client accounts, created 50+ interactive dashboards, reducing interpretation time by 50%.

Linguist Data Scientist, Computational Linguist - LinguaData

2019 - 2021

- Designed NLP models, improving multilingual processing accuracy by 25% for datasets spanning 120 languages.
- Escalated translation algorithms with syntactic parsing, reducing error rates by 30% and supporting 50,000+ translation requests.
- Increased real-time language recognition and context-aware translations by 40%.

SKILLS

- Programming Languages: Python, R, SQL, Java, Julia, Matlab, Scala, Rust, Perl, TCL, Erlang/Elixir, Wolfram, C, C++, JavaScript, XML.
- Tools & Frameworks: Proficient in machine learning and AI tools (Keras, TensorFlow, PyTorch, Scikit-learn, Pandas, NumPy), data visualization and BI tools (Tableau, Power BI, Matplotlib, Seaborn), and big data technologies (Apache Spark, Hadoop, DynamoDB).
- Core Competencies: Strategic Trading Systems, Machine Learning, Artificial Intelligence, Natural Language Processing.
- Languages: Arabic, German, Italian, French, Mandarin, and English.

EDUCATION

Stanford University, Stanford School of Medicine

Major: Biomedical Data Science

Minor: Deep Learning and AI for Healthcare

Coursework: Research Ethics, Data Analysis, Cloud Computing, Bioinformatics, Genomics, AI/ML, Medical Software, Neural Networks, Large Language Models, Epigenetics, Transcriptomics, Proteomics, Clinical and Wearable Data, Imaging Data, Medical Data Science, Bioengineering, Surgical Robotics, AI in Medicine.

WorldQuant University

Master of Science: Financial Engineering

Minor: Applied AI & Data Science

Relevant Coursework: Risk Management, Optimization, Data Science, Computational Finance, Statistical Analysis, Algorithmic Trading, Predictive Modeling, Advanced Statistical Techniques, Decision Trees, Linear Regression, Time-Series Analysis.

Ibn Tofail University

(Graduated at top of class, GPA:3.9/4.0)

Bachelor of Arts (B.A.), Linguistics (cum laude) with a Minor in Natural Language Processing

Research: "Computational linguistics roles in developing Artificial Intelligence with a Focus on Semantic Role Labeling and Multilingual NLP"

Related Studies: Machine Learning, Computational Linguistics, Natural Language Processing, Data Structures, Algorithms, Statistical Modeling, and Deep Learning. Awards: HCIA-Cloud Computing V5.0, HCIA-Big Data V3.0, HCIA-Cloud Service V3.0, HCIA-Datacom V1.0, HCIA AI V3.5.

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Neuroinformatics, Brain-Machine Interfaces, Digital Twin Technology, Quantum NLP, Ethical AI, Algorithmic Governance, Biomedical/Medical Data Science, Applied AI, Computational Linguistics, Corpus Linguistics, and Cryptologic Language Analytics.

CERTIFICATIONS

• AWS Cloud Practitioner, Microsoft DP- 600, Google Data Analytics, Meta Data Analyst, IBM Data Analyst, IBM Data Analytics with Excel and R, IBM Data Science, Fractal Data Science, IBM Data Engineer, Meta Database Engineer, and Google Cloud Data Analytics (More).

COURSEWORK

Stanford University: CS106A, CS106B, CS109, CS110. AI CS221, ML CS229, NLP CS224N, CS224S, CS224W, CS246, CS329X, EE263, DATASCI 112.

Harvard University: CS50, CS50 for JDs, CS50 for MBA, CS100, CS164, CS E-23a, CS E-33a, CS E-39b, CS E-80, CS E-75, CS E-76, CS E-295.

Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health: DS101 (R Basics, Visualization, Probability, Inference and Modeling, Wrangling, Regression).

Gies College of Business – UIUC: ACCT 100, ACCT 200, ACCT 300, FIN 200, ECON 101, ECON 102, FIN 101, FIN 200, FIN 200.

MIT OpenCourseWare: 6.0001, 6.0002, 6.005, 6.006, 6.009, 6.031, 6.033, 6.034, 6.036, 6.041A, 6.042J, 6.004, 6.028, 6.046J, 6.828, 6.829, 6.841, 6.852, 6.853,

6.864, 6.868, 6.8000, 6.801, 6.803, 6.820, 6.825, 6.832, 6.231, 6.437, 6.438, 6.867, 6.869, 15.071, 15.075J, IDS.012, IDS.131, 14.310x, Mega-R1-R7.